Guide to the Radio Haiti Papers, circa 1934-2003, bulk 1968-2003 RL.11499
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Radio Haiti papers
circa 1934-2003, bulk 1968-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Radio Haiti-Inter
RL.11499
80 Linear Feet 197 boxes; 2 oversize folders; and digital photographs
Radio Haïti-Inter was Haiti's first and most prominent independent radio station from the early 1970s until 2003. Under the direction of Jean Léopold Dominique and Michèle Montas, Radio Haiti was a voice of social change and democracy, speaking out against oppression and impunity while advocating for human rights and celebrating Haitian culture and heritage. The Radio Haiti papers contain mainly the station's on-air scripts and research materials covering a wide variety of subjects. The Radio Haiti audio recordings are described in a separate collection guide.
Arrangement
In keeping with Radio Haiti's original order, the papers are organized by subject. It should be noted that these subjects frequently overlap (for example, materials about repression of peasant farmers by the army in the late 1980s can be found under "Army," "Human Rights," "Peasant Movements" and "Provisional Governments").
Biographical / Historical
Radio Haïti-Inter was Haiti's first and most prominent independent radio station from the early 1970s until 2003. Under the direction of Jean Léopold Dominique and Michèle Montas, Radio Haiti was a voice of social change and democracy, speaking out against oppression and impunity while advocating for human rights and celebrating Haitian culture and heritage. The Radio Haiti papers contain mainly the station's on-air scripts and research materials.
The Radio Haiti collection is perhaps the most thorough documentation of late 20th century Haitian politics and history, including but not limited to the Duvalier regime and its aftermath; the nascent democratic movement amid military rule under the Conseil National de Gouvernement in the late 1980s; the first presidency, overthrow, return, and second presidency of Jean-Bertrand Aristide; the aftermath of the 1991-1994 coup years during which Haiti's democratically-elected government was in exile; and the first presidency of René Préval. Radio Haiti both covered and spoke out against impunity, calling for justice for victims of human rights violations and political oppression as well as victims of corruption and corporate malfeasance. With his background as an agronomist, Jean Dominique focused in particular on the political and land rights of dispossessed peasant farmers and the need for Haiti to strengthen and support national agricultural production. Radio Haiti advocated for freedom of the press and documented repression of the independent media, covered grassroots organizations and women's rights campaigns. Radio Haiti covered international relations, including the plight of undocumented Haitian refugees fleeing to the United States or the Bahamas (so-called "boat people"), Haitian cane-cutters in the Dominican Republic and repatriations of Haitian people from the Dominican Republic, US policy toward Haiti and US involvement in Haitian politics, neoliberal reform and structural adjustment policies. Radio Haiti promoted and showcased Haitian art and culture, including painting and sculpture, literature, poetry, theatre, music, history and national heritage, and other intellectual production. They highlighted Vodou as a meaningful and important part of national culture worthy serious analysis. The station focused extensively on key moments of repression and injustice, such as the 1987 Jean Rabel massacre of peasant farmers and the 1994 Raboteau massacre of Aristide partisans by the military and FRAPH paramilitary, and on important assassinations and disappearances, including but certainly not limited to liberation theology priests Jean-Marie Vincent and Jean "Ti Jan" Pierre-Louis, and, of course, the hired killing of Radio Haiti's own director, Jean Léopold Dominique.
Radio Haiti afforded as much consideration and airtime to the voices and concerns of peasant farmers from rural Haiti, members of grassroots organizations, Haitian braceros living on Dominican bateys, and residents of poor urban neighborhoods as it did to prominent politicians and intellectuals. By reporting largely in Haitian Creole, the language that all Haitians speak and understand, Radio Haiti made media and communication truly democratic, and showed Creole could be a language of serious political and intellectual inquiry.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Radio Haiti Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Related Materials
Radio Haiti audio recordings [collection guide]
Radio Haiti audio recordings [digital collection]
Collection Overview
Radio Haiti was based in downtown Port-au-Prince on Rue du Quai until 28 November 1980, when Jean-Claude Duvalier's government cracked down on the independent press and human rights activists. Radio Haiti was ransacked, and the station's journalists were arrested then exiled. Many, though not all, of the paper record from the 1970s were destroyed in the 1980 crackdown. Radio Haiti reopened after Duvalier fell in 1986, in a new building on Route Delmas. The station closed again after the 30 September 1991 coup d'état that overthrew President Jean-Bertrand Aristide, and reopened in 1995 after the democratic government was restored. As a result of the repression the station and its journalists endured, most of the materials in Radio Haiti's paper archive span 1986 to 1991, and 1995 to 2003, though it also contains extensive external print materials (mainly newspapers and magazines) that Jean Dominique collected while in exile from 1980 to 1986 and from 1991 to 1994.
"Radio Haiti materials" refers to documents created by Radio Haiti's staff. These are mainly on-air scripts, but also include notes and correspondence. "External materials" refers to materials created by outside sources, which were used for research purposes by Radio Haiti's staff. These include, but are not limited to, press (Haitian, Haitian diaspora, and international news outlets), press releases, petitions and open letters from grassroots groups and civil society organizations, reports and other publications, and government communiqués and decrees.
Radio Haiti-Inter; Human Rights; Human Rights -- Haiti; Vodou; Radio stations; Broadcast journalism; Arts, Haitian; Haitian literature; Editorials; Radio scripts; Haiti; Haiti -- History -- Coup d'état, 1991; Haiti -- History -- American intervention, 1994-1995; Haiti -- History; Haiti -- Politics and government; Haiti -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Photographs; Montas, Michèle, 1946; Dominique, Jean L. (Jean Leopold); Duvalier, François, 1907-1971; Duvalier, Jean-Claude, 1951-2014; Aristide, Jean-Bertrand
- Agriculture, 1975-2003
  - Agrarian reform, 1995-2002; 7 folders (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    See also: ODVA
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the agrarian reform experiment, particularly about the Institut National de la Réforme Agraire.
  - Agricultural credit, 1977-1980; 1987-1989; 2000; 1 folder (Box 2)
    See also: Cotton; Rice
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about agricultural credit, including the BCA (Bureau de Crédit Agricole), the BNDAI (Banque Nationale de Développement Agricole et Industriel) and the IDAI (Institut de Developpement Agricole et Industries).
  - ANDAH, 1980-1988; 1 folder (Box 2)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Association Nationale des Agro-professionnels haïtiens (ANDAH).
  - Aquaculture, 1976-2002; 1 folder (Box 2)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about aquaculture, fish farms, and fishing.
  - Bananas, 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 2)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to banana and plantain production in Haiti, particularly in the Arcahaie region.
  - Chickens, 1987-2002; 1 folder (Box 2)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about chicken breeding.
  - Coffee, 1978-2002; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about coffee production in Haiti, including activities of the FACN (Fédération des Associations Caféières Natives) and the Haitian Bleu project.
  - Cotton, 1987-1989; 1 folder (Box 2)
    See also: Agricultural credit
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about cotton production in the Artibonite.
  - Creole pig (1-3), 1978-1999; 3 folders (Box 2)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the elimination of the Creole pig. Includes the PEPPADEP campaign to eliminate swine flu, 1982 report by Jean-Jacques Honorat on swine flu, the attempted repopulation projects by Caritas, the care and feeding of imported pigs, attempts to find justice for farmers whose pigs were destroyed (including denunciations from many grassroots and civil society groups), and other materials.
  - Creole pig (4-6), 1978-1999; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Diseases, 1991-2001; 1 folder (Box 3)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about plant diseases and blights, including sheath rot (maladie de la paille noire), coconut disease, coffee borer beetles (scolyte), and anthrax, among others.
  - Domestic production, 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 3)
    See also: ODVA; KOZEPEP
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about domestic agricultural production.
  - External cooperation, 1987-2002; 1 folder (Box 3)
    See also: International relations; MARNDR
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about external cooperation on agricultural projects, including China, the US, France, Cuba, the European Union, South-South cooperation, FICA-CIARA.
  - Fairs, 1999-2002; 1 folder (Box 3)
    See also: Domestic production
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about agricultural fairs showcasing Haitian products. Includes commemorations of May 1 (International Workers' Day).
  - Fenitrothion, 1983-1984; 1987; 1 folder (Box 3)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the spraying of the insecticide fenitrothion as a malaria control measure and peasant farmers' resistance to the spraying of fenitrothion, particularly in Desarmes.
  - Fertilizer, 1996-2003; 1 folder (Box 3)
    See also: ODVA; agrarian reform; KOZEPEP
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about fertilizer and conflicts over fertilizer distribution.
  - Food security and famine, 1995-2002; 2 folders (Box 3)
    See also: International aid
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about food security, food insecurity, and famine. Includes drought and famine in the Nord-Ouest, UN Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) projects, and other topics.
  - General, 1977-2002; 1 folder (Box 3)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials on a variety of topics related to agriculture, including prices of products, animal husbandry, bamboo furniture, handmade paper, unions, grassroots organizations, reforestation projects, the Vilaj Afrikòl Savann Dyàn, and Gérald Brisson's 1968 essay "Les relations agraires dans l'Haïti contemporaine," republished in Haïti Progrès.
  - Infrastructure, 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 3)
    See also: MARNDR; ODVA; Agrarian reform; Public works
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about agricultural infrastructure projects, including drainage, irrigation, catchment lakes.
  - Mango, 1987-2001; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about mango cultivation.
  - MARNDR, 1980; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Ministère de l'Agriculture, des Ressources Naturelles et du Développement Rural (MARNDR). Includes letter to Dieudonné Fardin of Le Petit Samedi Soir from Jean-Claude Boyer and Jean Robert Alexandre,
  - MARNDR, 1986-2002; 2 folders (Box 4)
    See also: Agrarian reform; ODVA
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Ministère de l'Agriculture, des Ressources Naturelles et du Développement Rural (MARNDR). Includes various rural development projects, agrarian reform, distribution of tools, reforestation projects, trainings.
  - ODVA, 1975-2001; 1 folder (Box 4)
    See also: Rice; Agrarian reform; Peasant movements.)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about ODVA (the Organisme de Développement de la Vallée de l'Artibonite).
  - Prices in public markets, 1977-1980; 1 folder (Box 4)
    See also: Informal sector
    MARNDR's daily surveys of prices of products (rice, beans, corn, various fruits and vegetables) in public markets in Port-au-Prince, including Marché Salomon, Croix-des-Bossales, and others.
  - Rice, 1990-2002; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about rice production (primarily in the Artibonite), the flooding of the Haitian market by imported US rice, and other subjects.
  - Sugar, 1973-2002; 3 folders (Box 4)
    See also: Peasant movements
    Radio Haiti materials and external materials about sugar production. Includes the closure of the HASCO factory, activities by the APDL (Association des Planteurs et des Distillateurs de Léogâne), the importation of ethanol as counterfeit clairin, the Darbonne sugar factory.
- Civil Society, 1973-2003
  - Churches, 1981-2003
    - Beauchamp affair, 1986; 1 folder (Box 5)
      Materials related to the October 1986 conflict between Adventists and liberation theology priest Reynald Clérismé and his supporters in Beauchamp, Nord-Ouest (near Jean-Rabel), concerning a food-for-work program.
    - Catholic Church (1-7 of 9), 1981-2003; 7 folders (Box 5)
      See also: Ti Legliz
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Catholic Church. Includes the Conférence Épiscopale d'Haïti; the Conférence Haïtienne des Religieux; the Commission Nationale Justice et Paix; materials related to Pope John Paul II's visit to Haiti in 1983; materials related to Bishops Romelus, Constant, Péan, and Miot; the Church's reactions to elections and electoral violence; the Church's reactions to military violence; divisions between traditional Church authorities and the "ti legliz" proponents of liberation theology.
    - Catholic Church (8-9 of 9), 1981-2003; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Expulsion of Father René Poirier, 1988; 1 folder (Box 6)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (including press statements) concerning the 1988 expulsion of Canadian priest Father René Poirier in Grand-Goâve by the military government.
    - General, 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 6)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Ministère des Cultes, collaborations between the Catholic and Protestant churches, and other topics.
    - Hunger strike, 1987; 2 folders (Box 6)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (including press statements and open letters) concerning the 1987 hunger strike in front of the Port-au-Prince Cathedral. Strikers called for Father Jean-Bertrand Aristide to remain in Haiti at Saint-Jean Bosco church.
    - Lafond Lapointe, 1990; 1 folder (Box 6)
      Materials sent to Radio Haiti by Anglican Reverand Lafond Lapointe, concerning an attempt on his life during the March 29, 1990 march, during which he was accused of being a Macoute.
    - Protestantism, 1990-2002, undated; 1 folder (Box 6)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to Protestant Churches, including relations with the Vodou sector and efforts to posthumously "convert" Boukman.
    - Ti Legliz, 1986-1990; 1 folder (Box 6)
      See also: Catholic Church, Jean-Rabel massacre, Saint-Jean Bosco massacre, Disappearance of Charlot Jacquelin, Freycineau; Organisations populaires
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Ti Legliz movement, liberation theology, Ti Kominote Legliz (TKL), and Caritas. Includes reactions to the disappearance of Charlot Jacquelin (1986) and the Freycineau attack (1987).
  - Civil society organisations, 1996-1997
    - General, 1996-1997; 1 folder (Box 7)
      External materials about a variety of civil society organizations, including employers' associations (associations patronales), Initiatives Démocratiques, ASOSYE, Centre d'Information et d'Éducation Civique (CIEC), Christian Peacemaker Teams, Institut Culturel Karl Lévêque, Comité d'Initiative Patriotique de la Société Civile (CIDSC), and others. Also includes reactions to political crisis from Catholic priests Yvon Massac, Joachim Samedi, and William Smarth, as well as Monsignor Romelus.
  - Demonstrations, 1995-2003
    - Protests and strikes, general, 1995-2002; 3 folders (Box 7)
      See also: Organisations populaires; Labor unions and rights; Insecurity; Peasant rights; Political crisis
      Radio Haiti folders and external materials about protests, marches demonstrations, general strikes, and riots, including those organized by OPs, political groups, peasant farmers, merchants, and other groups.
  - Labor unions and rights, 1977-2003
    - C.G.T., 1990-1997; 1 folder (Box 7)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Centrale Générale des Travailleurs (C.G.T.).
    - Chauffeurs, 1986-1990; 4 folders (Box 7)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Syndicat des chauffeurs de transport public de la zone métropolitaine (SCTPM), the Union des conducteurs privés et publics de Port-au-Prince, the Centrale syndicale des trasnporteurs haïtiens, and other transportation unions. Includes transportation strikes to protest the government of Prosper Avril.
    - General, 1977-1980; 1 folder (Box 8)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to labor unions, labor conflicts, strikes, and workers' rights. Includes an open letter from construction foremen to Secretary of State for Labor Hubert de Ronceray, an open letter from the Syndicat des Travailleurs de la Brasserie La Couronne to de Ronceray, and news from 1984 about the death of Haitian labor leader Ulrick Joly in Paris.
    - General, 1986-1989; 7 folders (Box 8)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to labor unions, labor conflicts, and workers' rights, including the code de travail. Labor unions include CATH-CLAT (Centrale Autonome des Travailleurs Haïtiens/Centrale Latino-Américaine des Travailleurs), FOS (Fédération des Ouvriers Syndiqués), KOTA (Confédération des ouvriers et des travailleurs haïtiens), and OGITH (Organisation Générale Indépendante des Travailleurs Haïtiens).
    - General, 1986-1989; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - General, 1990-1991; 2 folders (Box 9)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to labor unions, labor conflicts, and workers' rights. Labor unions include CATH-CLAT (Centrale Autonome des Travailleurs Haïtiens/Centrale Latino-Américaine des Travailleurs), Confédération des travailleurs haïtiens (CTH), OGITH (Organisation Générale Indépendante des Travailleurs Haïtiens), and transportation unions.
    - General, 1995-1998; 4 folders (Box 9)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to labor unions, labor conflicts, and workers' rights. Labor unions include CATH-CLAT, CTH, FOS, CNEH (Confédération nationale des enseignants haïtiens), transportation unions, the EDH (Électricité d'Haïti) employees' union, the SONAPI (Société Nationale des Parcs Industriels) employees' union, transportation unions, Haitian unions in the Dominican Republic, and others.
    - General, 1999-2003; 2 folders (Box 9)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to labor unions, labor conflicts, and workers' rights. Labor unions include CTH, KOTA, FOS, EDH, nurses' and transportation unions, among others.
    - Health care, 1995-2003; 3 folders (Box 10)
      See also: HUEH; Health
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to the Syndicat du personnel infirmier, the Syndicat des Travailleurs de Santé, conflicts and strikes at the General Hospital (HUEH), strikes my medical residents and medical technicians, strikes at hospitals throughout Haiti.
    - Labor protection, 1995-1999; 1 folder (Box 10)
      Radio Haiti materials related to labor protection and insurance, particularly for state employees. Includes ONA (Office National d'Assurance-Vieillesse), OFATMA (Office d'Assurance Accidents du Travail, Maladie et Maternité), and OAVCT (Office Assurance Véhicules Contre Tiers).
    - Strikes and demonstrations, 1995-2003; 4 folders (Box 10)
      See also: Public administration
      Radio Haiti scripts related to labor protests, demonstrations, and strikes, many of which concern civil servants and public employees. Includes employees of the DGI (Direction Générale des Impôts), Ministry of Social Affairs, post office, Autorité Portuaire Nationale (APN), Télécom, Ministry of the Interior, various municipal governments. Also includes transportation strikes, Association nationale des distributeurs de produits pétroliers (ANADIPP), EDH, public prosecutors and court clerks, and others.
    - Protests and demonstrations: Education, 1995-2003; 3 folders (Box 11)
      See also: Education
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials related to strikes, protests, and demonstrations from the education sector. Includes the CNEH, conflicts with the Ministry of Education, public and private schools, university faculty and students, and other subjects.
  - Organisations populaires, 1995-2003
    - General, 1995-2003; 4 folders (Box 11)
      See also: Insecurity; Demonstrations; Political crisis; Fanmi Lavalas; Aristide
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about organisations populaires (OPs), many of them affiliated with Fanmi Lavalas, including TKL, JPP, JTT, Espas Konsètasyon Oganizasyon Popilè Granmoun yo, APN, and others. Includes partisans of Félix "Gwo Fefe" Bien-Aimé, René Civil, Paul Raymond, Sò Ann, Jean-Claude Nord, Michel-Ange "Bora" Phillis, and Amiot Métayer. Also includes the violent protests that broke out at the funeral of Father Jean Pierre-Louis. Also includes smaller community organizations.
  - Peasant movements, 1986-2003
    - Artibonite rice wars, 1986; 1 folder (Box 12)
      See also: Rice
      Radio Haiti scripts and external materials related to the 1986 "rice wars" in the Artibonite, in which farmers from L'Estère blocked imported "Miami rice" coming from Gonaïves.
    - KOZEPEP, 2000-2002; 1 folder (Box 12)
      Radio Haiti scripts relating to the activities of KOZEPEP, including aggression against KOZEPEP and its leader, Charles Suffrard.
    - Land conflicts, 1987-1991; 2 folders (Box 12)
      See also: Army; Peasant rights; Repression; Chefs de section; Provisional governments; Jean-Rabel massacre; Massacres
      Radio Haiti scripts and external materials related to land conflicts throughout Haiti, including Liancourt, Latapie, Grand-Bois, Verrettes, Marchand Dessalines, and other places in the Artibonite.
    - Land conflicts, 1995-2003; 3 folders (Box 12)
      Radio Haiti scripts and external materials related to land conflicts throughout Haiti, particularly in the Artibonite (Desdunes, Bocozelle, the Pérodin massacre), Bois Dumay, Musseau Village, and elsewhere.
    - Mouvman Peyizan Papay, 1986-2001; 3 folders (Box 12)
      See also: MPKNP
      Radio Haiti scripts and external materials relating to the activities of Mouvman Peyizan Papay (MPP). Includes MPP's position on the elimination of the creole pig and agrarian reform, among other subjects.
    - Mouvman Peyizan Papay (crisis), 1990; 2 folders (Box 13)
      MPP's materials relating to an internal crisis in 1990, involving former employee Herns Marcelin.
    - Mouvman Peyizan Sidès, 1989-1990; 1 folder (Box 13)
      Press releases from Mouvman Peyizan Sidès.
    - MPKNP, 1996-2001; 1 folder (Box 13)
      See also: Mouvman Peyizan Papay